<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Connectors in Teiid</title>
  <para>A connector handles all communications with individual enterprise information sources, which can include
    databases, data feeds, flat files, etc.</para>
  <para>A connector is used to:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Translate a Teiid-specific command into a native command.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Execute the command.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Return batches of results.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>Teiid is responsible for reassembling the results from one or more connectors into an
    answer for the user’s command.</para>
  <para>
    For a more detailed workflow, see the chapter
    <link linkend="connector_api">
      <emphasis>“Connector API.”</emphasis>
    </link>
  </para>
  <sect1>
    <title>Do You Need a New Connector?</title>
    <para>Teiid provides several connectors for common enterprise information system types. If
      you can use one of these enterprise information systems, you do not need to develop a custom one.
    </para>
    <para>Teiid offers the following connectors:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>JDBC:</emphasis>
          Connects to many relational databases. The JDBC Connector is validated against the following database
          systems: Oracle, Microsoft SQL Server, IBM DB2, MySQL, Postgres, Derby, Sybase, H2, and HSQL. In addition, the JDBC Connector can
          often be used with other 3rd-party drivers and provides a wide range of extensibility options to
          specialize behavior against those drivers.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Text:</emphasis>
          Connects to text files.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>XML</emphasis>
          Connects to XML files on disk or by invoking Web services on other enterprise systems.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>LDAP</emphasis>
          Connects to LDAP directory services.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Salesforce</emphasis>
          Connects to Salesforce.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Required Items to Write a Custom Connector</title>
    <para>To write a connector, follow this procedure:</para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>Gather all necessary information about your Enterprise Information System (EIS). You will need
          to know:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>API for accessing the system</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configuration and connection information for the system</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Expectation for incoming queries/metadata</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The processing constructs, or capabilities, supported by information system.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Required properties for the connector, such as URL, user name, etc.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Implement the required interfaces defined by the Connector API.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Connector – starting point.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Connection – represents a connection to the source.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>ConnectorCapabilities – specifies what kinds of commands your connector can
              execute</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Execution (and sub-interfaces) – specifies how to execute each type of command</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Test your connector with Connector Development Kit (CDK) test utilities.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Deploy your connector type into Teiid.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create and import your connector type definition file.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a connector binding using the connector type</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Deploy a Virtual Database with metadata corresponding to your EIS</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Execute queries via Teiid.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      This guide covers how to do each of these steps in detail. It also provides additional information for
      advanced topics, such as connection pooling, streaming large objects, and transactions. For a sample
      connector code, please check the <ulink url="http://teiid.org">Teiid community</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>