<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="download">
  <title>Download</title>
  <para>
    Before you begin, download binaries for
    <ulink url="http://jboss.org/federate/download">Federate Embedded</ulink>. 
    Note that there are three different artifacts are available for download.</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>Federate Source - contains all the source code for all modules</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Federate Binary - contains all the binary code for all modules</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Federate Embedded Kit - contains only required modules and their required 3rd party dependencies</para></listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para> Download Federate Embedded Kit and expand this tar/zip file in a known accessible location. </para>
    
  <para>In the expanded directory, you will find "federate-${version}-embedded.jar" which is the required binary jar file for
    Federate Embedded and all the files under the "lib" directory are supporting 3rd party binaries
    required to execute Federate Embedded. Later sections will go in detail about installing these artifacts.</para>
  <para>In the expanded directory, you will find "federate-${version}-embedded.jar", which is the main binary jar file for
    Federate Embedded, and the "lib" directory containing supporting 3rd party binaries
    required to execute Federate Embedded.</para>
  <note>
    <para>
      Access to the physical data sources such as Oracle, MS-SQL Server, DB2, and Sybase through Federate relies
      upon user supplying their own JDBC drivers in the deployment. Open source JDBC drivers for MySQL, Postgres, and Derby were 
      already included in the "lib" folder as the LGPL license permits them. However, Federate code
      base has been tested extensively with <ulink url="http://www.datadirect.com">DataDirect</ulink> JDBC Drivers and 
      for your convenience DataDirect drivers are available through this site to be used with your 
      Federate Embedded application. Note that you would have agree for separate licensing terms set forth by DataDirect 
      before you use them. For more information and directions to download check out
      <ulink url="http://jboss.org/federate/datadirect">DataDirect driver download</ulink>
    </para>
  </note>
</chapter>