<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % CustomDTD SYSTEM "../../../../../../docbook/custom.dtd">
%CustomDTD;
]>
<chapter id="develop_adapter">
	<title>Developing JEE Connectors</title>
	<para>This chapter examines how to use facilities provided by the Teiid
		API to develop a JEE JCA Connector. Please note that these are 
        standard JEE JCA connectors, nothing special needs to be done for Teiid. As an aid to our Translator 
        developers, we provided a base implementation framework.
        If you already have a JCA Connector or some other mechanism to get data from your source system, you can skip this chapter.</para>

    <para>If you are not familiar with JCA API, please read the JCA 1.5 Specification at <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/connector/"/>. 
    There are lot of online tutorials on how to design and build a JCA Connector. The below we show you to build very simple connector, 
    however building actual connector that supports transactions, security can get much more complex.</para>
    
    <para>Refer to the JBoss Application Server Connectors documentation at <ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/jbossas/jboss4guide/r4/html/ch7.chapt.html"/>.</para>
	
    <section>
		<title>Using the Teiid Framework</title>
        <para>If you are going to use the Teiid framework for developing a JCA connector, follow these steps. The required classes are in
        <code>org.teiid.resource.api</code> package. Please note that Teiid framework does not make use JCA's CCI framework, only the JCA's SPI interfaces. </para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Define Managed Connection Factory</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Define the Connection Factory class</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Define the Connection class</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Define the configuration properties in a "ra.xml" file</para>
            </listitem>    
        </itemizedlist>

        <section id="managed_connection_factory">
            <title>Define Managed Connection Factory</title>
            <para>Extend the <code>BasicManagedConnectionFactory</code>, and provide a implementation for the 
            "createConnectionFactory()" method. This method defines a factory method that can create connections.</para>
            
            <para>This class also defines configuration variables, like user, password, URL etc to connect to the EIS system. Define an 
            attribute for each configuration variable, and then provide both "getter" and "setter" methods for them. 
            Note to use only "java.lang" objects as the attributes, DO NOT use Java primitives for defining and accessing the properties.
            See the following code for an example.</para>
            <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class MyManagedConnectionFactory extends BasicManagedConnectionFactory 
{
   @Override
   public Object createConnectionFactory() throws ResourceException 
   {
      return new MyConnectionFactory();
   }

   // config property name (metadata for these are defined inside the ra.xml)
   String userName;
   public String getUserName()          {  return this.userName;  }
   public void setUserName(String name){  this.userName = name;  }

   // config property count  (metadata for these are defined inside the ra.xml)
   Integer count;
   public Integer getCount()            {  return this.count;  }
   public void setCount(Integer value) {  this.count = value; }               

}]]></programlisting>
        </section>
		<section>
			<title>Define the Connection Factory class</title>
			<para>Extend the <code>BasicConnectionFactory</code> class, and provide a implementation for the "getConnection()" method.</para>
          <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class MyConnectionFactory extends BasicConnectionFactory 
{
   @Override
   public MyConnection getConnection() throws ResourceException 
   {
      return new MyConnection();
   }  
}]]></programlisting>
          <para>Since the Managed connection object created the "ConnectionFactory" class it has access to all the configuration 
          parameters, if "getConnection" method needs to do pass any of credentials to the underlying EIS system. 
          The Connection Factory class can also get reference to the calling user's <code>javax.security.auth.Subject</code> during 
          "getConnection" method by calling  
          </para>
          <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><![CDATA[Subject subject = ConnectionContext.getSubject();]]></programlisting>      
          <para>
          This "Subject" object can give access to logged-in user's credentials and roles that are defined. Note that this may be null.
          </para>
          <para>Note that you can define "security-domain" for this resource adapter, that is separate from 
          the Teiid defined "security-domain" for validating the JDBC end user. However, it is users responsibility to make the necessary
          logins before the Container's thread accesses this resource adapter, and this can get overly complex.</para>
		</section>
        
        <section id="connection">
            <title>Define the Connection class</title>
            <para>Extend the <code>BasicConnection</code> class, and provide a implementation based on your access 
            of the Connection object in the Translator. If your
            connection is stateful, then override "isAlive()" and "cleanup()" methods and provide proper implementations. These are called
            to check if a Connection is stale or need to flush them from the connection pool etc. by the Container.</para>
          <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class MyConnection extends BasicConnection 
{
   public void doSomeOperation(command)
   {
      // do some operation with EIS system..
      // This is method you use in the Translator, you should know
      // what need to be done here for your source..
   }
     
   @Override
   public boolean isAlive() 
   {
      return true;
   }
   
   @Override
   public void cleanUp() 
   {
         
   }
}]]></programlisting> 
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>XA Transactions</title>
            <para>If your EIS source can participate in XA transactions, then on your Connection object, 
            override the "getXAResource()" method and provide the "XAResource" object for the EIS system.
            Refer to <xref linkend="connection"/>.
            Also, You need to extend the "BasicResourceAdapter" class and provide implementation for method
            "public XAResource[] getXAResources(ActivationSpec[] specs)" to participate in crash recovery. </para>
            
            <para>Note that, only when the resource adapters are XA capable, then Teiid can make them participate in a distributed
            transactions. If they are not XA capable, then source can participate in distributed query but will not participate 
            in the transaction. Transaction semantics are defined by how you you configured "connection-factory" in a "resource-adapter". i.e. jta=true/false.</para>
        </section>        
        
        <section>
            <title>Define the configuration properties in a "ra.xml" file</title>
            <para>
            Define a "ra.xml" file in "META-INF" directory of your RAR file.  
            An example file is provided in <xref linkend="appendix_a"/>.
            </para>
            <para>
            For every attribute defined inside the your ManagedConnectionFactory
             class, define the following XML configuration for that attribute  inside the "ra.xml" file. 
             These properties are used by user to configure instance of this Connector inside a 
            Container. Also, during the startup the Container reads these properties from this file and knows how to inject 
            provided values in the "-ds.xml" file into a instance of "ManagedConnectionFactory" to create the Connection.
            Refer to <xref linkend="managed_connection_factory"/>.
            </para>
          <programlisting role="XML" language="XML"><![CDATA[<config-property>
   <description>
      {$display:"${display-name}",$description:"${description}", $allowed="${allowed}", 
      $required="${true|false}", $defaultValue="${default-value}"}
   </description>
   <config-property-name>${property-name}</config-property-name>
   <config-property-type>${property-type}</config-property-type>
   <config-property-value>${optioal-property-value}</config-property-value>
</config-property>]]></programlisting> 
           
           <para>The format and contents of "&lt;description&gt;" element may be used as extended metadata for tooling.  The special format must begin and end with curly braces e.g. {...}.  This use of the special format and all properties is optional.  Property names begin with '$' and are separated from the value with ':'.  Double quotes identifies a single value.  A pair of square brackets, e.g. [...], containing comma separated double quoted entries denotes a list value. 
            <itemizedlist>
            	<para>Extended metadata properties</para>
                <listitem>
                    <para>$display: Display name of the property</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>$description: Description about the property</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>$required: The property is a required property; or optional and a default is supplied</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>$allowed: If property value must be in certain set of legal values, this defines all the allowed values</para>
                </listitem>    
                <listitem>
                  <para>$masked: The tools need to mask the property; Do not show in plain text; used for passwords</para>
                </listitem>   
                <listitem>
                  <para>$advanced: Notes this as Advanced property</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>$editable: Property can be modified; or read-only</para>
                </listitem> 
            </itemizedlist>
           
           Note that all these are optional properties; however in the absence of this metadata, Teiid tooling may not work as expected.
           
           </para>
        </section>        
	</section>

   <section id="ra_package">
        <title>Build and Package the Adapter</title>
        <para>Once all the required code is developed, it is time to package them into a RAR artifact, that can be deployed
        into a Conainer. A RAR artifact is lot more similar to a WAR. To put together a RAR file it really depends upon 
        build system you are using.</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Eclipse: You can start out with building Java Connector project, it will produce the RAR file</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ant: If you are using "ant" build tool, there is "rar" build task available</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Maven: If you are using maven, use &lt;packaging&gt; element value as "rar". Teiid uses maven, you can look at any of
              the "connector" projects for sample "pom.xml" file. Here is sample pom.xml file.</para>
              
              <programlisting role="XML" language="XML"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<project xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/maven-v4_0_0.xsd" 
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
   <modelVersion>4.0.0</modelVersion>
   <artifactId>connector-{name}</artifactId>
   <groupId>org.company.project</groupId>
   <name>Name Connector</name>
   <packaging>rar</packaging>
   <description>This connector is a sample</description>

   <dependencies>
      <dependency>
         <groupId>org.jboss.teiid</groupId>
         <artifactId>teiid-api</artifactId>
         <scope>provided</scope>
      </dependency>
      <dependency>
         <groupId>org.jboss.teiid</groupId>
         <artifactId>teiid-common-core</artifactId>
         <scope>provided</scope>
      </dependency>
      <dependency>
         <groupId>javax.resource</groupId>
         <artifactId>connector-api</artifactId>
         <scope>provided</scope>
      </dependency>
   </dependencies>

</project>]]></programlisting>                
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
        <para>Make sure that the RAR file, under its "META-INF" directory has the "ra.xml" file.  If you are using maven 
        refer to <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-rar-plugin/"/>.  In the root of the RAR file, 
        you can embed the JAR file containing your connector code and any dependent library JAR files. </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="dependencies">
        <title>Adding Dependent Libraries</title>
        <para>Add MANIFEST.MF file in the MATA-INF directory, and the following line to add the core Teiid API dependencies for 
        resource adapter. <emphasis>Dependencies: org.jboss.teiid.common-core,org.jboss.teiid.api,javax.api</emphasis> 
        If your resource adapter depends upon any other third party jar files, .dll or .so files they can be placed at the
        root of the rar file. If any of these libraries are already available as modules in JBoss AS, then you can add the module
        name to the above MANIFEST.MF file to define as dependency.
        </para>
    </section>
    
   <section id="ra_deploy">
        <title>Deploying the Adapter</title>
        <para>Once the RAR file is built, deploy it by copying the RAR file into "deploy" directory of JBoss AS's choosen profile. 
        Typically the server does not need to be restarted when a new RAR file is being added. Alternatively, you can also use 
        "admin-console" a web based monitoring and configuration tool to deploy this file into the container. </para>
        
        <para>Once the Connector's RAR file is deployed into the JBoss container, now you can start creating a instance of this
        connector to be used with your Translator. Creating a instance of this Connector is no different than creating a 
        "Connection Factory" in JBoss AS. Again, you have have two ways you can create a "ConnectionFactory".</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                Edit standalone.xml or domain.xml file, and add following XML in the "resource-adapters" subystem.
                </para>
                <programlisting language="XML" role="XML"><![CDATA[<!-- If susbsytem is already defined, only copy the contents under it and edit to suit your needs -->
<subsystem xmlns="urn:jboss:domain:resource-adapters:1.0">
    <resource-adapters>
        <resource-adapter>
            <archive>teiid-connector-sample.rar</archive>
            <transaction-support>NoTransaction</transaction-support>
            <connection-definitions>
                <connection-definition class-name="org.teiid.resource.adapter.MyManagedConnectionFactory"  jndi-name="${jndi-name}" 
                        enabled="true" 
                        use-java-context="true" 
                        pool-name="sample-ds">
                      <config-property name="UserName">jdoe</config-property>
                      <config-property name="Count">12</config-property>
                </connection-definition>
            </connection-definitions>
        </resource-adapter>
    </resource-adapters>
</subsystem>]]></programlisting>     
                <para>  
                There are lot more properties that you can define for pooling, transactions, security etc in this file. 
                Check JBoss AS documentation for all the avaialble properties.           
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Alternatively you can use the web based "admin-console" configration and monitoring program, to create a new 
                Connection Factory. Just have your RAR file name and needed configuration properties handly and fill out web form 
                and create the ConnectionFactory.</para>
            </listitem>

         </itemizedlist>        
    </section>    
</chapter>