<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="deployment">
  <title>Deployment</title>
  <para> Having built the VDB, it must be deployed into Teiid server, so it can be accessed through a JDBC connection.</para>

  <para />
  <para>This example deploys Teiid within a JBoss AS. The sample deployment is shown below.
  You can find more details about deploying to application servers on the Teiid web-site</para>
  <para />
  <section id="teiid-runtime">
    <title>JBoss AS Application Deployment</title>
    
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Before we can deploy the VDB to the server, we need to create and deploy the required Connection Factories for Derby
        and File sources. Connection Factories are sources that provide the data then their data is integrated through Teiid. If you are
        familiar with creating data sources or connection factories in JBoss AS, then this is exactly the same operation. 
        </para>
        
        <para>Access to Derby first requires that the the Derby client jar (${derby-install}/lib/derbyclient.jar) be placed in the ${jboss-install}/server/{profile}/lib directory.</para>
        
        <para>See or copy the following:</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[${teiid-examples}/dynamicvdb-portfolio/portfolio-ds.xml
${teiid-examples}/dynamicvdb-portfolio/marketdata-file-ds.xml]]> </programlisting>  
        <para>files into "${jboss-install}/server/{profile}/deploy" directory to create the Derby and File data sources respectively.</para>
      </listitem>      
      <listitem>
        <para>The above data sources provide the data to your VDB. Now to deploy your VDBl place your VDB file (either the dynamicvdb-portfolio/portfolio-vdb.xml file or the full .vdb file) in a the "${jboss-install}/server/{profile}/deploy" directory. 
        If the JBoss AS is not already started, start by running the "${jboss-install}/bin/run.sh" or "${jboss-install}/bin/run.bat" scripts. 
        Check the logs or the console to make sure there were no errors during the deployment of the VDB.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Now, go to the next section to learn how to
          <link linkend="OpenConnection">connect to the VDB</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>