<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="deployment">
  <title>Deployment</title>
  <para> Now that you have built the VDB, you are ready to deploy the VDB. Essentially once you deploy you can
    connect to VDB using JDBC connection. Note that there are two steps involved in this deployment</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Deploying Federate Embedded</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Deploying VDB</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para> Federate Embedded can be deployed in a couple different scenarios.</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        In a
        <link linkend="stand-alone-deployment">Stand-alone</link>
        Java application
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In a JEE Application Server (Deploy and Create connection pool).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para />
  <para>For this example purposes the stand-alone deployment explained below. However you can find more
    details about deploying to application servers on the Federate web-site</para>
  <para />
  <sect1 id="stand-alone-deployment">
    <title>Stand-alone Application Deployment</title>
    <para>Copy the "federate-${version}-embedded.jar" and all dependent jars in "lib" directory in your Java
      application's classpath along with your VDB. If your application is already using the any of dependent jars
      defined in "lib" directory you can safely ignore adding that jar file to the classpath. Make sure the that
      the versions match</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add "federate-${version}-embedded.jar" to your application classpath</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add all the dependent jar files in the "lib" directory ito your application's classpath. If your
          application is already using the any of dependent jars defined in "lib" directory you can safely ignore
          adding that jar file to the classpath. Make sure the that the versions match</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Place VDB in a folder and add this folder and add this folder to your applications classpath
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Now check out next section on how to
          <link linkend="OpenConnection">connect to the VDB</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>