<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="deployment">
  <title>Deployment</title>
  <para> Having built the VDB, it must be deployed so it can be access through a JDBC connection.
  Note there are two steps involved in this deployment:</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Deploying Teiid Embedded</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Deploying VDB</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para> Teiid Embedded is typically used in one of two manners:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        As a
        <link linkend="stand-alone-deployment">Stand-alone</link>
        Java application
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In a JEE Application Server (Deploy and Create connection pool).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para />
  <para>This example deploys Teiid Embedded as a stand-alone Java application. The sample deployment is shown below.
  You can find more details about deploying to application servers on the Teiid web-site</para>
  <para />
  <sect1 id="stand-alone-deployment">
    <title>Stand-alone Application Deployment</title>
    <para>Copy the "Teiid-${version}-embedded.jar" and all dependent jars in "lib" directory in your Java
      application's classpath along with your VDB. If your application is already using the any of dependent jars
      defined in "lib" directory you can safely ignore adding that jar file to the classpath. Make sure the that
      the versions match</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add "Teiid-${version}-embedded.jar" to your application classpath</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add all the dependent jar files in the "lib" directory to your application's classpath. If your
          application is already using the any of the "lib" directory's dependent jars, you can safely ignore
          adding that jar to the classpath. Make sure the versions match.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Place the VDB in a folder and add this folder to your application's classpath.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Now, go to the next section to learn how to
          <link linkend="OpenConnection">connect to the VDB</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>