<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="download">
  <title>Download</title>
  <para>
    Download binaries for
    <ulink url="http://jboss.org/federate/download">Federate Embedded</ulink>
    . Note that there are three different artifacts are available for download.
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Federate Source - contains all the source code for all modules</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Federate Binary - contains all the binary code for all modules</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Federate Embedded Kit - contains only required modules and their required 3rd party
        dependencies</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
    Download
    <emphasis> Federate Embedded Kit</emphasis>
    and expand this tar/zip file in a known accessible location.
  </para>
  <para>In the expanded directory, you will find "federate-${version}-embedded.jar" which is the required binary
    jar file for Federate Embedded and all the files under the "lib" directory are supporting 3rd party binaries
    required to execute Federate Embedded. Later in the guide we will go over the deployment.</para>
  <note>
    <para>
      Access to the physical data sources such as Oracle, MS-SQL Server, DB2, and Sybase through Federate relies
      upon user supplying their own JDBC drivers in the deployment. Federate code base has been tested extensively
      with
      <ulink url="http://www.datadirect.com">DataDirect</ulink>
      JDBC Drivers. For your convenience DataDirect drivers are available through Federate site to be used
      exclusively with your Federate Embedded application free of charge. Note that you would have agree for
      separate licensing terms set forth by DataDirect before you use them. For more information and directions to
      download check out
      <ulink url="http://jboss.org/federate/datadirect">DataDirect driver download</ulink>
    </para>
    <para>JDBC drivers for MySQL, Postgres,and Derby were already included in the "lib" folder as the LGPL
      license permits them to be included with the Federate Embedded kit.</para>
  </note>
</chapter>