<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="example-explained">
  <title>Example Explained</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Portfolio Application Explained</title>
    <para>Now let's start in building a small "Portfolio" example, that has accounts with multiple stock
      securities and let's you view up-to date value of an account based on the provided external market data. For
      example purposes the "Account" specific data exists in a relational database and the "market data" exists in
      a comma separated file (CSV). This example will take you through all the steps required in building virtual
      database (VDB) to integrate the both relational source and CSV file, then deploying VDB file and querying VDB
      through your application.</para>
    <figure id="steps">
      <title>Various Steps involved in creating the example</title>
      <graphic align="center" scale="100" fileref="../images/steps-defined.png" />
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <link linkend="step-1">Step-1: Create schema and load sample data in the Relational Database</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <link linkend="step-2">Step-2: Identify the CSV file and its contents</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <link linkend="step-3">Step-3: Build a VDB</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <link linkend="step-4">Step-4: Deploy the VDB</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <link linkend="step-5">Step-5: Access the VDB using JDBC API</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="step-1">
    <title>Step-1: Create schema and load sample data in the Relational Database</title>
    <para>
      In this example written using
      <ulink url="http://db.apache.org/derby/">"Derby"</ulink>
      as the relational database.
      <ulink url="http://db.apache.org/derby/derby_downloads.html">Download</ulink>
      and install Derby on your machine, or if you have access to installed instance use that instance. It is
      expected that you create a database called "accounts" in this Derby instance that is used by this example
      application.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para> you can substitute Derby for any database of your choice, as long as you have a JDBC driver to access
        it. The schema file defined below is specific to Derby, however it can be easily converted to other
        databases.</para>
    </note>
    <para>
      Below find the corresponding schema. For complete schema, please refer to
      <emphasis>"examples/portfolio/customer-schema.sql"</emphasis>
      file of the downloaded kit.
    </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[      
          - -Contains the name and address of a Customer who owns portfolio account 
          CREATE TABLE CUSTOMER
          (
             SSN char(10),
             FIRSTNAME varchar(64),
             LASTNAME varchar(64),
             ST_ADDRESS varchar(256),
             APT_NUMBER varchar(32),
             CITY varchar(64),
             STATE varchar(32),
             ZIPCODE varchar(10),
             PHONE varchar(15)
          );
          
          --Contains Customer's account number and its current status
          CREATE TABLE ACCOUNT
          (
             ACCOUNT_ID integer,
             SSN char(10),
             STATUS char(10),
             TYPE char(10),
             DATEOPENED timestamp,
             DATECLOSED timestamp
          );
          
          --Contains information about stock symbol, company name etc.
          CREATE TABLE PRODUCT (
             ID integer,
             SYMBOL varchar(16),
             COMPANY_NAME varchar(256)
          );
          
          --Contains each Account's holdings of Stocks   
          CREATE TABLE HOLDINGS
          (
             TRANSACTION_ID integer,
             ACCOUNT_ID integer,
             PRODUCT_ID integer,
             PURCHASE_DATE timestamp,
             SHARES_COUNT integer
          );                  
    ]]>
    </programlisting>
    <para>You need to start the Derby and create the "accounts" database with the above schema. The directions
      below are given for Linux environment, for starting the Derby instance, however find the similar commands if
      you are working with Windows environment. Start a terminal session, and change directory to where Derby is
      installed and execute following commands</para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
      export DERBY_HOME=`pwd`
      ./bin/startNetworkServer
    ]]>        
    </programlisting>
    <para>The above starts the Derby in network mode. Now, start another terminal and you need to use 'ij' tool
      of the Derby (like SQL*PLus for Oracle) to create the schema. Use the "customer-schema.sql" file in
      "examples/portfolio" directory. Note this script file also has some sample data in addition to above schema
    </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
      export DERBY_HOME=`pwd`
      ./bin/ij /path/to/customer-schema.sql
      ]]>        
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      Make sure that you did not have any issues in creating the schema needed for going forward in this example.
      You can use 'ij' tool to make sure the tables got created. or if you like use any tools like
      <ulink url="http://www.squirrelsql.org/">SQuirreL</ulink>
      , or
      <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/datatools/">Eclipse's Data Tools</ulink>
      plugin to connect to Derby instance and check the schema and sample data.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="step-2">
    <title>Step-2: Identify the CSV file and its contents</title>
    <para>In order to use a Text file as the source, we need to define two different types of files. A descriptor
      file and one or more data files. Conceptually, a Descriptor file defines schema, and each data file defines
      data inside a single table</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Text Descriptor File - The Text Descriptor file contains information that describes the structure
          of the data text file you want to use as a data source, path to the data file name and delimiter
          information inside the file etc. Shown below is an sample format of the file</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
            MarketData.Price.location = /path/to/marketdata-price.txt
            MarketData.Price.delimiter = ,
            MarketData.Price.headerLine = 1
         ]]>        
        </programlisting>
        <para>The below table shows some of the available properties that can be used in a Descriptor file. For
          full details look in Text File Connector documentation</para>
        <table frame="all">
          <title>Connection Properties</title>
          <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
            <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*" />
            <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*" />
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Property</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Description</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>location</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The path to the file on the local system or URL to remote file.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>delimiter</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The character the file uses to delimit the fields within each line in the file</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>headerLine</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The line number in on which the names of the columns are defined</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>skipHeaderLines</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The number of top lines to skip in a text file.(include one for the header)</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>note that each property line starts with "schema" information and followed by logical "table"
          name and then the "property". In the above sample file "MarketData" is "schema" information, "Price" is
          table name. This information defines text files as a sudo relational source to the Federate Embedded
          engine. The above defined content is for a 'single' table, however you can repeat those lines in defining
          multiple tables in the same Descriptor file but each "location" property for a given "table" needs to
          point to different data file.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data File: This is the file that is identified by "location" property in the Descriptor file. Each
          data file contains column information for the table and all the associated data for that table.
          The column information is typically defined on line 1 as header line in the file, and all the following
          lines contain the actual rows of data. Each single line corresponds to single row. The sample file is shown
          below. A complete sample file is in the "examples/portfolio/marketdata-price.txt" file</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
           SYMBOL,PRICE
           IBM,83.46
           MSFT,21.19
           RHT,11.84
           BA, 44.58
           ORCL,17.37           
         ]]>        
        </programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>Just locate the sample data files provided or create your own data files. Make sure that the
      descriptor file contains correct URL or the full path to the data file. Now, both our sources are ready to be
      used to build a VDB</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>